foreign
[Music]
the sum of the first K positive integers
is called the kth Triangular number is
denoted T sub K and can be visually
represented by a triangular array of
dots where there's K dots in the last
row and one dot in the first row in this
video we'll investigate divisibility of
triangular numbers by three
because we're dividing by three there
are three cases to consider suppose
first that we're looking at a triangular
array with 3K plus one dots in the base
so that we're looking at the 3K plus
first triangular a number then we can
focus on a trapezoidal array at the
bottom that has 2K plus 1 Dots and a
height of length K we can then take
three copies of this trapezoidal array
rotate it and move it around the diagram
so that it almost fills up the entire
diagram there's only one dot left over
this means that the 3K plus first
triangular number must be equal to one
plus three copies of the number of dots
in the trapezoidal array but the
trapezoidal array dots can be
represented as the 2K plus first
triangular number minus the K plus first
triangular number as it's really the
difference of two triangular arrays so
in this case the number of dots is
congruent to one mod 3. for our next
case let's suppose that the number of
dots in the base of the Triangular array
is divisible by three so that it's three
times k for some integer k then we're
looking at the array representing the
Triangular number T sub 3K this time we
can form a trapezoidal array in the
bottom left with two K dots in the
bottom and the height of size k then we
can rotate and shift three copies of
this trapezoidal array to perfectly fill
in the entire diagram this time this
means that t sub 3K is equal to 3 times
the number of dots in the trapezoidal
array which is given by the difference
of the 2K triangular number and the kth
Triangular number so in this case we see
that t sub 3K is congruent to 0 mod 3.
for our final case we imagine that our
triangular array has 3K plus two dots in
the base so that we're looking at T sub
three K plus 2. once again we form a
trapezoidal array in the bottom left
with a base consisting of two k plus 1
Dots and a height consisting of K plus 1
dots once again we can use three rotated
copies of this trapezoidal array of dots
to fill in the entire triangular array
that we're interested in this means that
t sub 3 K plus 2 is equal to 3 times the
number of dots in the trapezoidal array
which is given by the difference of the
2K plus first triangular number and the
kth Triangular number as shown in this
case we see that t sub 3 K plus 2 is
congruent to 0 mod 3. using these three
cases we see that t sub n is congruent
to 1 or 0 mod 3 and it's congruent to 1
if and only if n is congruent to 1 mod
3. check out the linked video for the
analogous result for square numbers